so we have seen that performing these
atomic read write operations on the lock
repeatedly
even while waiting for the lock is
inefficient in terms of energy and it
actually slows down the thread that is
in the critical section we want to make
this more efficient and one way of doing
that is to do a so-called test and
atomic op approach in the locking
function so the original approach to
using for example an atomic exchange is
to
set r1 to 1
and as long as r1 is one
try to swap it with lockvar
eventually we see a zero and we exit
but as we now know
this keeps invalidating everybody else
who is waiting on the log so we are
getting a lot of cash misses while
waiting and active waiting like this is
not only spending energy on the bus
transfers all the time but also
keeps the bus busy so that useful work
in other threads that are not busy
waiting is slowed down so this is kind
of like a repeated atomic op approach to
make it more efficient what we do is we
do the same type of looping here but we
don't immediately try to swap what we do
first is use normal loads to wait for
lockwork to become zero
so the idea is that we're using normal
loads while lockvar is busy if we
observe that it's free we try to grab it
by doing an atomic exchange we cannot
try to grab it using the normal store
that's why we have to do the exchange
but the idea is that there is no point
in trying to do the exchange unless the
lock is actually free and the purpose of
the exchange now is solely to ensure
that only one of us grabs the lock once
it becomes free but the busy waiting
while the lock is continuously free is
done using normal reads
so now if we have core 0 1 and 2 and
core 0 succeeds in doing an exchange and
gets the lock var in the modified state
core 1 will now reach this point and
read lockvar see that it's 1.
it's done using a normal load
so here we move to the own state
here we move to the shared state
and there is a cache to cash transfer
here now we will keep doing this
but we'll keep getting cash hit so we no
longer access the bus
while waiting
similarly core 2 will load the lock bar
it will also get
the value and have it in the shared
state
and now it also gets cash hits while
waiting so as long as core zero keeps
the lock busy here these two cores are
no longer generating bus traffic so core
zero basically gets the entire coherence
bus to itself so you can very quickly
service cash misses and cache hits here
are much more efficient than bus
accesses and this is going to continue
until core 0 releases the lock at which
point there is an invalidation and these
two will read again see a value of one
try to compete for it using the exchange
and so on but those bursts of activity
really happen only when they're actually
trying to acquire the lock as long as
the lock is really busy they just keep
using normal loads in this loop so this
is much more energy efficient